<!DOCTYPE HTML>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>Encrypted Media Extensions</title>
    <style>/* --- ISSUES/NOTES --- */
    div.issue-title, div.note-title {
        padding-right:  1em;
        min-width: 7.5em;
        color: #b9ab2d;
    }
    div.issue-title { color: #e05252; }
    div.note-title { color: #52e052; }
    div.issue-title span, div.note-title span {
        text-transform: uppercase;
    }
    div.note, div.issue {
        margin-top: 1em;
        margin-bottom: 1em;
    }
    .note > p:first-child, .issue > p:first-child { margin-top: 0 }
    .issue, .note {
        padding: .5em;
        border-left-width: .5em;
        border-left-style: solid;
    }
    div.issue, div.note {
        padding: 0.5em;
        margin: 1em 0;
        position: relative;
        clear: both;
    }
    span.note, span.issue { padding: .1em .5em .15em; }
    
    .issue {
        border-color: #e05252;
        background: #fbe9e9;
    }
    .note {
        border-color: #52e052;
        background: #e9fbe9;
    }
    </style>
    <style type="text/css">
      div.nonnormative { color: green; margin: 2em 0 2em 0em; padding: 0.5em 1em; border: none; background: #DDFFDD; }
      .nonnormative:before { display: table; margin: -1em -0.5em -0.5em auto; width: auto; content: 'This section is non-normative.'; color: black; font-style: italic; border: solid 2px; background: white; padding: 0 0.25em; }

      <!-- For inline non-normative text. -->
      .non-normative { font-style: italic; color: DarkSlateGrey; }
      .non-normative em { font-style: normal;}
      .non-normative var { font-style: normal;}
    </style>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="https://www.w3.org/StyleSheets/TR/w3c-ed.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="head">
      <p><a href="http://www.w3.org/"><img src="https://www.w3.org/Icons/w3c_home" alt="W3C" width="72" height="48" /></a></p>
      <h1>Encrypted Media Extensions</h1>
      <h2 id="draft-date">W3C Editor's Draft 7 November 2013</h2>
      <dl>
        <dt>This Version:</dt>
        <dd><a href="http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/default/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html">http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/default/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html</a></dd>
        <dt>Latest Published Version:</dt>
        <dd><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/encrypted-media/">http://www.w3.org/TR/encrypted-media/</a></dd>
        <dt>Latest editor's draft:</dt>
        <dd><a href="http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/default/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html">http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/default/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html</a></dd>
        <dt>Editors:</dt>
        <dd>David Dorwin, Google, Inc.</dd>
        <dd>Adrian Bateman, Microsoft Corporation</dd>
        <dd>Mark Watson, Netflix, Inc.</dd>
  <dt>Bug/Issue lists:</dt>
  <dd><a href='http://w3.org/brief/MjY5'>Bugzilla</a>, <a href='http://www.w3.org/html/wg/tracker/products/19'>Tracker</a></dd>
  <dt>Discussion list:</dt>
  <dd><a href='http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-html-media/'>public-html-media@w3.org</a></dd>
  <dt>Test Suite:</dt>
  <dd>None yet</dd>
      </dl>
    </div>

    <p class="copyright"><a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#Copyright">Copyright</a> &#169; 2013 <a href="http://www.w3.org/"><abbr title="World Wide Web Consortium">W3C</abbr></a><sup>&#174;</sup> (<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu/"><abbr title="Massachusetts Institute of Technology">MIT</abbr></a>, <a href="http://www.ercim.eu/"><abbr title="European Research Consortium for Informatics and Mathematics">ERCIM</abbr></a>, <a href="http://www.keio.ac.jp/">Keio</a>, <a href="http://ev.buaa.edu.cn/">Beihang</a>), All Rights Reserved. W3C <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#Legal_Disclaimer">liability</a>, <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#W3C_Trademarks">trademark</a> and <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/copyright-documents">document use</a> rules apply.</p>
    <hr/>

    <h2>Abstract</h2>

    <p>This proposal extends HTMLMediaElement providing APIs to control playback of protected content.</p>
    <p>The API supports use cases ranging from simple clear key decryption to high value video (given an appropriate user agent implementation).
    License/key exchange is controlled by the application, facilitating the development of robust playback applications supporting a range of content decryption and protection technologies.</p>
    <p>This specification does not define a content protection or Digital Rights Management system. Rather, it defines a common API that may be used to discover, select and interact with
    such systems as well as with simpler content encryption systems. Implementation of Digital Rights Management is not required for compliance with this specification: only the simple
    clear key system is required to be implemented as a common baseline.</p>
    <p>The common API supports a simple set of content encryption capabilities, leaving application functions such as authentication and authorization to page authors. This is achieved by
    requiring content protection system-specific messaging to be mediated by the page rather than assuming out-of-band communication between the encryption system and a license
    or other server.</p>
 
    <h2>Status of This Document</h2>

    <p><em>
      This section describes the status of this document at the time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document.
      A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision of this technical report can be found in the
      <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</a> at http://www.w3.org/TR/.
    </em></p>
    <p>Implementors should be aware that this specification is not stable. <strong>Implementors who are not taking part in the discussions are likely to find the specification changing out from under them in incompatible ways.</strong> Vendors interested in implementing this specification before it eventually reaches the Candidate Recommendation stage should join the mailing list mentioned below and take part in the discussions.</p>
    <p>
      This document was published by the <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/">HTML working group</a> as an Editor's Draft.
      Please submit comments regarding this document by using the W3C's (<a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/enter_bug.cgi?product=HTML%20WG&amp;component=Encrypted%20Media%20Extensions">public bug database</a>) with the product set to <kbd>HTML WG</kbd> and the component set to
      <kbd>Encrypted Media Extensions</kbd>.
      If you cannot access the bug database, submit comments to <a href="mailto:public-html-media@w3.org">public-html-media@w3.org</a>
      (<a href="mailto:public-html-media-request@w3.org?subject=subscribe">subscribe</a>,
      <a href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-html-media/">archives</a>) and arrangements will be made to transpose the comments to the bug database.
      All feedback is welcome.
    </p>
    <p>
      Publication as an Editor's Draft does not imply endorsement by the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be updated,
      replaced or obsoleted by other documents at any time. It is inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in progress.
    </p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: It is an open issue whether and how the spec should do more to encourage/ensure CDM-level interop. See <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=20944">Bug 20944</a>.</p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: This specification contains sections for describing <a href="#security">security</a> and <a href="#privacy">privacy</a> considerations. These sections are not final and are tracked in <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=22909">Bug 22909</a> and <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=22910">Bug 22910</a>.</p>
    <p>
      This document was produced by a group operating under the <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">5 February 2004 W3C Patent Policy</a>.
      W3C maintains a <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/01/pp-impl/40318/status" rel="disclosure">public list of any patent disclosures</a> made in connection with
      the deliverables of the group; that page also includes instructions for disclosing a patent. An individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which
      the individual believes contains <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#def-essential">Essential Claim(s)</a> must disclose the
      information in accordance with <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#sec-Disclosure">section 6 of the W3C Patent Policy</a>.
      </p>


    <h2 id="toc">Table of Contents</h2>

    <ul style="list-style-type:none">
      <li><a href="#introduction">1. Introduction</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#definitions">1.1. Definitions</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#extensions">2. Media Element Extensions</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#error-codes">2.1. Error Codes</a></li>
          <li><a href="#session-state">2.2. MediaKeySession States</a></li>
          <li><a href="#media-element-restictions">2.3. Media Element Restrictions</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#events">3. Events</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#event-definitions">3.1 Event Definitions</a></li>
          <li><a href="#event-summary">3.2 Event Summary</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#algorithms">4. Algorithms</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#algorithms-encrypted-stream">4.1. First Time a Key Reference is Encountered</a></li>
          <li><a href="#algorithms-enrypted-block">4.2. Encrypted Block Encountered</a></li>
          <li><a href="#algorithms-load">4.3. Addition to Media Element Load Algorithm</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#key-release">5. Key Release</a></li>
      <li><a href="#simple-decryption">6. Simple Decryption</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#simple-decryption-clear-key">6.1. Clear Key</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#security">7. Security Considerations</a></li>
      <li><a href="#privacy">8. Privacy Considerations</a></li>
      <li><a href="#containers">9. Container Guidelines</a></li>
        <li><ul style="list-style-type:none">
          <li><a href="#webm">9.1. WebM</a></li>
          <li><a href="#iso">9.2. ISO Base Media File Format</a></li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><a href="#examples">10. Examples</a></li>
      <li><a href="#revision-history">11. Revision History</a></li>
    </ul>


    <h2 id="introduction">1. Introduction</h2>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>
      This proposal allows JavaScript to select content protection mechanisms, control license/key exchange, and implement custom license management algorithms.
      It supports a wide range of use cases without requiring client-side modifications in each user agent for each use case.
      This also enables content providers to develop a single application solution for all devices.
      A generic stack implemented using the proposed APIs is shown below.
      This diagram shows an example flow: other combinations of API calls and events are possible.
    </p>
    <img src="stack_overview.svg" alt="A generic stack implemented using the proposed APIs" height="700"></img>

    <h3 id="definitions">1.1. Definitions</h3>
    <p>Text in <span class="non-normative">this font and color</span> is non-normative.</p>

    <h4 id="cdm">1.1.1. Content Decryption Module (CDM)</h4>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>The Content Decryption Module (CDM) is a generic term for a part of or add-on to the user agent that provides functionality for one or more <a href="#key-system">Key Systems</a>.
    Implementations may or may not separate the implementations of CDMs and may or may not treat them as separate from the user agent.
    This is transparent to the API and application.
    A user agent may support one or more CDMs.</p>

    <h4 id="key-system">1.1.2. Key System</h4>
    <p>A Key System is a generic term for a decryption mechanism and/or content protection provider.
    Key System strings provide unique identification of a Key System.
    They are used by the user agent to select the <a href="#cdm">Content Decryption Modules</a> and identify the source of a key-related event.
    <a href="#simple-decryption">Simple Decryption</a> Key Systems are supported by all user agents. User agents may also provide additional CDMs with corresponding Key System strings.
    </p>

    <p>A Key System string is always a reverse domain name. <span class="non-normative">For example, "com.example.somesystem".</span>
    Key System strings are compared using case-sensitive matching. <span class="non-normative">It is recommended that CDMs use simple lower-case ASCII key system strings.</span></p>

    <p class="non-normative">
    Within a given system ("somesystem" in the example), subsystems may be defined as determined by the key system provider.
    For example, "com.example.somesystem.1" and "com.example.somesystem.1_5".
    Key System providers should keep in mind that these will be used for comparison and discovery, so they should be easy to compare and the structure should remain reasonably simple.
    </p>

    <h4 id="key-session">1.1.3. Key Session</h4>
    <p>A Key Session, or simply Session, represents the lifetime of the key(s) it contains and associates all messages related to them.
    Sessions are embodied as <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> objects.
    Each Key session is associated with a single instance of <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> provided in the <methodref>createSession</methodref> call.
    </p>

    <h4 id="session-id">1.1.4. Session ID</h4>
    <p>A Session ID is a unique string identifier generated by the user agent or CDM that can be used by the application to identify <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> objects.
    <span class="non-normative">(The underlying content protection client or server do not necessarily need to support Session IDs.)</span>
    </p>

    <p>A new Session ID is generated each time the user agent successfully initializes a <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.
    It must be valid before the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> enters the <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef> or <coderef prefix="state">READY</coderef> states and the user agent fires the associated events.
    </p>

    <p>Each Session ID shall be unique within the browsing context in which it was created.
    <span class="non-normative">(Note: Some use cases may require that Session IDs be unique within the origin over time, including across browsing sessions.)</span>
    </p>

    <h4 id="initialization-data">1.1.5. Initialization Data</h4>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>Initialization Data is a generic term for container-specific data that is used by <a href="#cdm">Content Decryption Modules</a> to generate a key request.
    It should always allow unique identification of the key or keys needed to decrypt the content, possibly after being parsed by a CDM or server.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#key-system">Key Systems</a> usually require a block of initialization data containing information about the stream to be decrypted before they can construct a key request message.
    This block could be as simple as a key or content ID to send to a server or as complex as an opaque Key System-specific collection of data.
    This initialization information may be obtained in some application-specific way or may be stored with the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>.
    Container formats may provide for storage of such information, possibly for multiple <a href="#key-system">Key Systems</a> in a single media file.
    </p>

    <p>Initialization data found in the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> is provided to the application in the <coderef>initData</coderef> attribute of the <coderef>needkey</coderef> event.
    This data has a container-specific format and is assumed to contain one or more generic or Key System-specific sets of initialization information.
    </p>

    <h4 id="cross-origin-support">1.1.6. Cross Origin Support</h4>
    <p>During playback, embedded media data is exposed to script in the embedding origin. In order for the API to fire <coderef>needkey</coderef>
    and <coderef prefix="event">message</coderef> events, <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> must be <cors-same-origin/> with the embedding page.
    If <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> is cross-origin with the embedding document, authors should use the <videoanchor name="attr-media-crossorigin">crossorigin</videoanchor> attribute
    on the <a href="#media-element">media element</a> and CORS headers on the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> response to make it <cors-same-origin/>.
    </p>

    <h2 id="extensions">2. Media Element Extensions</h2>
    <p>We extend <dfn id="media-element" title="media element"><media-element/></dfn> to allow decryption key acquisition to be handled in JavaScript.</p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: For some <a href="#cdm">CDMs</a>, "key" and "key request" correspond to "license" and "license request", respectively.</p>

    <pre class="idl">
partial interface <precodedfn>HTMLMediaElement</precodedfn> {
  // Encrypted Media
  readonly attribute <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef> <precoderef>keys</precoderef>;
  void <premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(<precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef> mediaKeys);
  
  attribute <EventHandler/> <precoderef>onneedkey</precoderef>;
};

[<a href="#dom-media-keys-constructor">Constructor</a> (DOMString <a href="#key-system">keySystem</a>)]
interface <precodedfn>MediaKeys</precodedfn> {
  readonly attribute DOMString <precoderef>keySystem</precoderef>;

  <precoderef>MediaKeySession</precoderef> <premethodref>createSession</premethodref>(DOMString type, Uint8Array initData);

  static bool <premethodref>isTypeSupported</premethodref>(DOMstring <a href="#key-system">keySystem</a>, DOMString? type);
};

interface <precodedfn>MediaKeySession</precodedfn> : <dom4ref name="eventtarget">EventTarget</dom4ref> {
  // error state
  readonly attribute <precoderef>MediaKeyError</precoderef>? <precoderef>error</precoderef>;

  // session properties
  readonly attribute DOMString <precoderef>keySystem</precoderef>;
  readonly attribute DOMString <precoderef>sessionId</precoderef>;

  // session operations
  void <premethodref>update</premethodref>(Uint8Array response);
  void <premethodref>release</premethodref>();
};

partial interface <precodedfn>HTMLSourceElement</precodedfn> {
  attribute DOMString <precoderef prefix="source">keySystem</precoderef>;
};</pre>

    <p>The <codedfn>keys</codedfn> attribute is the <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> being used when decrypting encrypted <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> for this <a href="#media-element">media element</a>.</p>
    <p>The <methoddfn name="setMediaKeys">setMediaKeys</methoddfn> method provides the <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> to use. When calling this method, the media element must run the following steps:</p>
    
    <ol>
      <li><p>If loading has not started, throw an <invalid-state-err/> exception and abort these steps.</p>
      <p class="non-normative">In general, applications should wait for an event named <coderef>needkey</coderef> or <videoref name="event-media-loadstart">loadstart</videoref> (per the <resource-fetch-algorithm/>) before calling this method.</p>
      </li>
      <li><p>If the <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> object is already in use and the user agent is unable to re-use it with this element, throw a <quota-exceeded-err/> exception and abort these steps.</p></li>
      <li>Set the <coderef>keys</coderef> attribute of the media element to <var>mediaKeys</var>.</li>
    </ol>
    
    <p class="non-normative">Note: In some implementations, <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> objects created by <methodref>createSession</methodref> may not fire any events until the <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> object is associated with a media element with <methodref>setMediaKeys</methodref>.</p>

    <p>The <codedfn>onneedkey</codedfn> event handler for the <coderef>needkey</coderef> event must be supported by all HTMLMediaElements as both a content attribute and an IDL attribute.</p>

    <p>The <dfn id="dom-media-keys-constructor"><code>MediaKeys(<var title="true">keySystem</var>)</code></dfn> constructor must run the following steps:</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>If <var title="true">keySystem</var> is null or an empty string, throw an <invalid-access-err/> exception and abort these steps.</p></li>
      <li><p>If <var title="true">keySystem</var> is not one of the user agent's supported <a href="#key-system">Key Systems</a>, throw a <not-supported-err/> and abort these steps. Key system string comparison is case-sensitive.</p></li>
      <li>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> object.
        <ol>
          <li><p>Let the <coderef>keySystem</coderef> attribute be <var title="true">keySystem</var>.</p></li>
        </ol>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>The user agent will asynchronously execute the following steps:</p>
        <ol>
          <li><p>Let <var title="true">cdm</var> be the <a href="#cdm">content decryption module</a> corresponding to <var title="true">keySystem</var>.</p></li>
          <li><p>Load <var title="true">cdm</var> if necessary.</p></li>
          <li>
            <dl class="switch">
              <dt>If <var title="true">cdm</var> fails to load or initialize</dt>
              <dd><ol>
                <li><p>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> object with the following attributes:</p>
                  <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                    <coderef>code</coderef> = the appropriate <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> code<br></br>
                    <coderef>systemCode</coderef> = a Key System-specific value, if provided, and 0 otherwise
                  </li></ul>
                </li>
                <li><p>Store this new error object internally with the <codref>MediaKeys</codref> instance being created. This will be used to fire an error against any session created for this instance.</p></li>
              </ol></dd>
            </dl>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </li>

      <li>Return the new <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> object to the caller.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>The <codedfn>keySystem</codedfn> attribute is an identifier for the <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> being used.</p>

    <p>The <methoddfn name="createSession">createSession(<var title="true">type</var>, <var title="true">initData</var>)</methoddfn> method must run the following steps:</p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: The contents of <var title="true">initData</var> are container-specific <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a>.
    <var title="true">type</var> specifies the container type and thus how to interpret <var title="true">initData</var>. 
    </p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: MIME types usually include "audio/" or "video/", and these should be included in <var title="true">type</var> as appropriate.
    However, user agents and <a href="#cdm">CDMs</a> should not treat sessions created with "audio/" differently than those created with "video/".
    That is, there is no such thing as an "audio session" or a "video session" - all sessions are used for all media streams processed by <var title="true">cdm</var>.
    </p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>If <var title="true">type</var> contains a MIME type that is not supported or is not supported by the <coderef>keySystem</coderef>, throw a <not-supported-err/> exception and abort these steps.</p></li>

      <li><p>Let <var title="true">cdm</var> be the <var title="true">cdm</var> loaded in the <a href="#dom-media-keys-constructor"><code>MediaKeys</code> constructor</a>.</p></li>

      <li>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.
        <ol>
          <li><p>Let the <coderef>keySystem</coderef> attribute be <var title="true">keySystem</var>.</p></li>
          <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">CREATED</coderef>.</p></li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      
      <li><p>Add the new object to an internal list of session objects.</p></li>

      <li><p>
        If there is a <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> stored with the <coderef>MediaKeys</coderef> object that occurred because of an error loading the <var title="true">cdm</var>
        then <queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">error</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object and abort these steps.
      </p></li>

      <li><p>Schedule a task to initialize the session, providing <var title="true">type</var>, <var title="true">initData</var>, and the new object.</p>
        <p>The user agent will asynchronously execute the following steps in the task:</p>
        <ol>
          <li><p>Let <var title="true">request</var> be null.</p></li>
          <li><p>Let <var title="true">defaultURL</var> be null.</p></li>
          <li><p>Use <var title="true">cdm</var> to execute the following steps:</p>
            <ol>
              <li><p>Process <var title="true">type</var> and <var title="true">initData</var>.</p>
              <p class="non-normative">Note: <var title="true">type</var> should be used to determine how to interpret <var title="true">initData</var>.</p>
              </li>
              <li><p>If a message exchange <span class="non-normative">(e.g. a license request)</span> is required:</p>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Let <var title="true">request</var> be a request generated by the <a href="#cdm">CDM</a> using <var title="true">initData</var>.</p>
                    <p><var title="true">cdm</var> must not use any stream-specific data, including <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>, not provided via <var title="true">initData</var>.</p>
                    <p class="non-normative">Note: <var title="true">request</var> may be a request for multiple keys, depending on the <var title="true"><a href="#key-system">keySystem</a></var> and/or <var title="true">initData</var>. This is transparent to the application.</p>                
                  </li>
                  <li><p>If <var title="true">initData</var> indicates a default URL relevant to <var title="true">keySystem</var>, let <var title="true">defaultURL</var> be that URL.</p></li> 
                </ol>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li><p>Let the <coderef>sessionId</coderef> attribute be a unique <a href="#session-id">Session ID</a> string. <span class="non-normative">It may be obtained from <var title="true">cdm</var>.</span></p></li>
          <li><p>If any of the preceding steps in the task failed, run the following steps:</p>
              <ol>
                <li><p>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> object with the following attributes:</p>
                  <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                    <coderef>code</coderef> = the appropriate <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> code<br></br>
                    <coderef>systemCode</coderef> = a Key System-specific value, if provided, and 0 otherwise
                  </li></ul>
                </li>
                <li><p>Set the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object's <coderef>error</coderef> attribute to the error object created in the previous step.</p></li>
                <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">ERROR</coderef>.</p></li>
                <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">error</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p></li>
                <li><p>Abort the task.</p></li>
              </ol>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>If the associated <a href="#media-element">media element(s)</a> are <a href="#waiting-for-a-key">waiting for a key</a>, <queue-a-task/> to attempt to resume playback.</p>
            <p class="non-normative">In other words, resume playback if the necessary key is provided.</p>
            <p>The user agent may choose to skip this step if it knows resuming will fail <span class="non-normative">(i.e.  no usable key was added)</span>.</p>
          </li>
          <li><p>Follow the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
            <dl class="switch">
              <dt>If <var title="true">request</var> is not null</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef>.</p></li>
                  <li>
                    <p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">message</coderef> at the new object.</p>
                    <p>The event is of type <coderef>MediaKeyMessageEvent</coderef> and has:</p>
                    <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                      <coderef>message</coderef> = <var title="true">request</var><br></br>
                      <coderef>destinationURL</coderef> = <var title="true">defaultURL</var>
                    </li></ul>
                  </li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
              <dt>Otherwise</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">READY</coderef>.</p></li>
                  <li>
                    <p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">ready</coderef> at the new object.</p>
                    <p class="non-normative">Note: this step makes it possible for a MediaKeySession to transition from the CREATED state to the READY state.
                    User agents might do this as an optimization but, even if this is done, all MediaKeySession instances must appear distinct regardless of the underlying implementation.</p>
                  </li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      <li>Return the new object to the caller.</li>
      <p class="non-normative">Note: User agents should always fire an event at the returned object in response to this call.
      For some implementations, it is possible - especially the first time a <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> is used - that the first event will be delayed significantly while the client is initialized, the user responds to permission requests, etc.
      Applications should expect and handle such delays.</p> 
    </ol>

    <p>The <methoddfn name="isTypeSupported">isTypeSupported(<var title="true">keySystem</var>, <var title="true">type</var>)</methoddfn> method returns whether <var title="true">keySystem</var> is supported with the specified container and codec <var title="true">type</var>(s).</p>
    <div class="example">
      <p>The following list shows some examples.</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>Returns whether the Some System <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> is supported. Specific containers and codecs may or may not be supported with Some System.</dt>
        <dd><pre class="code">MediaKeys.isTypeSupported("com.example.somesystem")</pre></dd>
        <dt>Returns whether the Some System <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> is present and supports the container and codec(s) specified by <var title="true">mimeType</var>.</dt>
        <dd><pre class="code">MediaKeys.isTypeSupported("com.example.somesystem", <var title="true">mimeType</var>)</pre></dd>
        <dt>Returns whether the user agent supports <a href="#simple-decryption-clear-key">Clear Key</a> <a href="#simple-decryption">Simple Decryption</a> of the container and codec(s) specified by <var title="true">mimeType</var>.</dt>
        <dd><pre class="code">MediaKeys.isTypeSupported("org.w3.clearkey", <var title="true">mimeType</var>)</pre></dd>
      </dl>
    </div>
    
    <p>It must run the following steps:</p>
    
    <ol>
      <li><p>If <var title="true">keySystem</var> contains an unrecognized or unsupported <a href="#key-system">Key System</a>, return false and abort these steps. Key system string comparison is case-sensitive.</p></li>
      <li><p>If <var title="true">type</var> is null or an empty string, return true and abort these steps.</p></li>
      <li><p>If the <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> specified by <var title="true">keySystem</var> does not support decrypting the container and/or codec specified by <var title="true">type</var>, return false and abort these steps.</p></li>
      <li><p>Return true.</p></li>
    </ol>

    <p>The <codedfn>error</codedfn> attribute is a <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> representing the current error state of the session. It is null if there is no error.</p>

    <p>The <codedfn>sessionId</codedfn> attribute is the <a href="#session-id">Session ID</a> for this object and the associated key(s) or license(s).</p>

    <p>The <methoddfn name="update">update(<var title="true">response</var>)</methoddfn> method must run the following steps:</p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: The contents of <var title="true">response</var> are <var title="true"><a href="#key-system">keySystem</a></var>-specific.</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>If the argument is null or an empty array, throw an <invalid-access-err/>.</p></li>
      <li><p>If the session is not in the <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef> state, throw an <invalid-state-err/>.</p></li>

      <li><p>Schedule a task to handle the call, providing <var title="true">response</var>.</p>
        <p>The user agent will asynchronously execute the following steps in the task:</p>
        <ol>
          <li><p>Let <var title="true">cdm</var> be the <var title="true">cdm</var> loaded in the <a href="#dom-media-keys-constructor"><code>MediaKeys</code> constructor</a>.</p></li>
          <li><p>Let <var title="true">request</var> be null.</p></li>
          <li><p>Use <var title="true">cdm</var> to execute the following steps:</p>
            <ol>
              <li><p>Process <var title="true">response</var>.</p>
                <p class="non-normative">Note: When <var title="true">response</var> contains key(s) and/or related data, <var title="true">cdm</var> will likely store the key and related data indexed by key ID.</p>
                <p class="non-normative">Note: The replacement algorithm within a session is <a href="#key-system">Key System</a>-dependent.</p>
                <p class="non-normative">Note: Keys from different sessions should be stored independently such that closing one session does not affect keys in other sessions, even if they have overlapping key IDs.</p>
                <p class="non-normative">Note: It is recommended that CDMs support a standard and reasonably high minimum number of keys per <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object, including a standard replacement algorithm, and a standard and reasonably high minimum number of <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> objects.
                This enables a reasonable number of key rotation algorithms to be implemented across user agents and may reduce the likelihood of playback interruptions in use cases that involve various streams in the same element (i.e. adaptive streams, various audio and video tracks) using different keys.
                </p>
              </li> 
              <li><p>If another message needs to be sent to the server, let <var title="true">request</var> be that message.</p></li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li><p>If any of the preceding steps in the task failed, run the following steps:</p>
              <ol>
                <li><p>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> object with the following attributes:</p>
                  <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                    <coderef>code</coderef> = the appropriate <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> code<br></br>
                    <coderef>systemCode</coderef> = a Key System-specific value, if provided, and 0 otherwise
                  </li></ul>
                </li>
                <li><p>Set the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object's <coderef>error</coderef> attribute to the error object created in the previous step.</p></li>
                <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">ERROR</coderef>.</p></li>
                <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">error</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p></li>
                <li><p>Abort the task.</p></li>
              </ol>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>If the associated <a href="#media-element">media element(s)</a> are <a href="#waiting-for-a-key">waiting for a key</a>, <queue-a-task/> to attempt to resume playback.</p>
            <p class="non-normative">In other words, resume playback if the necessary key is provided.</p>
            <p>The user agent may choose to skip this step if it knows resuming will fail <span class="non-normative">(i.e.  no usable key was added)</span>.</p>
          </li>
          <li><p>Follow the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
            <dl class="switch">
              <dt>If <var title="true">request</var> is not null</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef>.</p></li>
                  <li>
                    <p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">message</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p>
                    <p>The event is of type <coderef>MediaKeyMessageEvent</coderef> and has:</p>
                    <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                      <coderef>message</coderef> = <var title="true">request</var><br></br>
                      <coderef>destinationURL</coderef> = null
                    </li></ul>
                  </li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
              <dt>Otherwise</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">READY</coderef>.</p></li>
                  <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">ready</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p></li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </li>
      </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p>The <methoddfn name="release">release()</methoddfn> method allows an application to indicate to the system that it may release any resources associated with the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>. It must run the following steps:</p>

     <ol>
       <li><p>If the state of the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> is <coderef prefix="state">CLOSED</coderef> then abort these steps.</p></li>
       <li><p>If the state of the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> is <coderef prefix="state">ERROR</coderef>, throw an <invalid-state-err/> exception and abort these steps.</p></li>
       <li><p>Follow the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
            <dl class="switch">
              <dt>If the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> supports secure key release</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p class="issue">TODO: describe secure key release moving the session to PENDING state, firing message event, and then eventually moving to CLOSED. See <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=17199">Bug 17199</a>.</p></li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
              <dt>Otherwise</dt>
              <dd>
                <ol>
                  <li><p>Implementations may clear the internal state associated with the session, including keys and licences, to release resources but are not required to do so.</p>
                  <p class="non-normative">Note: the release() method is intended to act as a hint to the user agent that the application believes the MediaKeySession is no longer needed. The user agent may coordinate
                  with the associated CDM to determine whether resources can now be released.</p></li>
                  <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">CLOSED</coderef>.</p></li>
                  <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">closed</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p></li>
                </ol>
              </dd>
            </dl>
       </li>
    </ol>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: Keys in other sessions should be unaffected, even if they have overlapping key IDs.</p>

    <p>The <codedfn prefix="source">keySystem</codedfn> attribute of <coderef>HTMLSourceElement</coderef> specifies the <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> to be used with the <videoref name="media-resource">media resource</videoref>.
    The <resource-selection-algorithm/> is modified to check the <coderef prefix="source">keySystem</coderef> attribute after the existing <em>step 5</em> of the <em>Otherwise</em> branch of <em>step 6</em>:
    </p>
    <ol start="6">
      <li><p>&#8987; If <var title="">candidate</var> has a <coderef prefix="source">keySystem</coderef> attribute whose value represents a <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> that the user agent knows it cannot use with <videoref name="attr-source-type">type</videoref>, then end the <synchronous-section/>, and jump down to the <i title="">failed</i> step below.</p></li>
    </ol>

    <h3 id="error-codes">2.1. Error Codes</h3>
    <div class="issue"><div class="issue-title"><span>Issue 1</span></div><p class=""><a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=21798">Bug 21798</a> - Some errors may change or be removed.</p></div>
    <p><videoref name="mediaerror">MediaError</videoref> is extended, and a new error type is added.</p>
    <pre class="idl">
partial interface <precodedfn>MediaError</precodedfn> {
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_ERR_ENCRYPTED</precoderef> = 5;
};

interface <precodedfn>MediaKeyError</precodedfn> {
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_UNKNOWN</precoderef> = 1;
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_CLIENT</precoderef> = 2;
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_SERVICE</precoderef> = 3;
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_OUTPUT</precoderef> = 4;
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_HARDWARECHANGE</precoderef> = 5;
  const unsigned short <precoderef>MEDIA_KEYERR_DOMAIN</precoderef> = 6;
  readonly attribute unsigned short <precoderef>code</precoderef>;
  readonly attribute unsigned long <precoderef>systemCode</precoderef>;
};</pre>
    <dl class="domintro">
     <dt><var title="">session</var> . <var title="">error</var> . <coderef>code</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the current error's error code, from the list below.</p>
     </dd>
     <dt><var title="">session</var> . <var title="">error</var> . <coderef>systemCode</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the current error's system code.</p>
     </dd>
    </dl>

    <p>The <codedfn prefix="mediaerror">code</codedfn> attribute of a <coderef>MediaError</coderef> may additionally return the following:</p>
    <dl>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_ERR_ENCRYPTED</codedfn> (numeric value 5)</dt>
      <dd>The stream could not be played because it is encrypted and one of the following is true:
        <ol>
          <li>The media element does not have a <coderef>needkey</coderef> handler</li>
          <li>The media element's <coderef>keys</coderef> attribute is null</li>
        </ol>
        <p class="non-normative">Applications that support encrypted media should provide a <coderef>needkey</coderef> handler and/or call <methodref>setMediaKeys</methodref> no later than when <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> is provided.</p>
        <p class="non-normative">If the user agent does not support decryption of this <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>, it should report the same error it would for any other unsupported media data (e.g. <videoref name="dom-mediaerror-media_err_src_not_supported">MEDIA_ERR_SRC_NOT_SUPPORTED</videoref>).</p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <div class="impl">
    <p>The <codedfn>code</codedfn> attribute of a <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> object must return the code for the error, which must be one of the following:</p>
    <dl>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_UNKNOWN</codedfn> (numeric value 1)</dt>
      <dd>An unspecified error occurred. This value is used for errors that don't match any of the following codes.</dd>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_CLIENT</codedfn> (numeric value 2)</dt>
      <dd>The <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> could not be installed or updated.</dd>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_SERVICE</codedfn> (numeric value 3)</dt>
      <dd>The message passed into <coderef>update</coderef> indicated an error from the license service.</dd>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_OUTPUT</codedfn> (numeric value 4)</dt>
      <dd>There is no available output device with the required characteristics for the content protection system.</dd>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_HARDWARECHANGE</codedfn> (numeric value 5)</dt>
      <dd>A hardware configuration change caused a content protection error.</dd>
      <dt><codedfn>MEDIA_KEYERR_DOMAIN</codedfn> (numeric value 6)</dt>
      <dd>An error occurred in a multi-device domain licensing configuration. <span class="non-normative">The most common error is a failure to join the domain.</span></dd>
    </dl>

    <p>The <codedfn>systemCode</codedfn> attribute of a <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object is a <a href="#key-system">Key System</a>-dependent status code for the error that occurred.
    <span class="non-normative">This allows a more granular status to be returned than the more general <coderef>code</coderef>.</span>
    It should be 0 if there is no associated status code or such status codes are not supported by the Key System.
    </p>
    </div>

    <h3 id="session-state">2.3 MediaKeySession States</h3>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>Each <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> maintains an internal state that determines what events may be fired.</p>
    <h4 id="session-state-list">2.3.1 MediaKeySession State Definitions</h4>
    <p>The following table describes the possible states:</p>
    
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>State name</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="state">CREATED</codedfn></td>
          <td>The <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> has been created with a <methodref>createSession</methodref> call.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="state">PENDING</codedfn></td>
          <td>A <coderef prefix="event">message</coderef> event has been fired at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>. A call to <methodref>update</methodref> is expected next. The <a href="#media-element">media element</a> may block waiting for a key if encrypted data is encountered.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="state">READY</codedfn></td>
          <td>A <coderef prefix="event">ready</coderef> event has been fired at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>. The <a href="#media-element">media element</a> should not need to block waiting for a key if encrypted data associated with this session is encountered.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="state">ERROR</codedfn></td>
          <td>A <coderef prefix="event">error</coderef> event has been fired at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>. The <coderef>error</coderef> attribute of the session holds information about the most recent error.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="state">CLOSED</codedfn></td>
          <td>A <coderef prefix="event">closed</coderef> event has been fired at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>. No further events will be fired at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>.</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    
    
    <h4 id="session-state-transitions">2.3.2 MediaKeySession State Transitions</h4>
    <p>The following diagram shows the possible state transitions and the events fired when changing state:</p>
    <p><img src="session_state.svg" width="528" height="408" alt="State transition diagram"/></p>
    <p class="issue">TODO: Need to update the state diagram with CLOSED state.</p>
    
    <h3 id="media-element-restictions">2.3 Media Element Restrictions</h3>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>Media data processed by a CDM may not be available through Javascript APIs in the usual way (for example using the CanvasRenderingContext2D drawImage() method and the AudioContext MediaElementAudioSourceNode).
    This specification does not define conditions for such non-availability of media data, however, if media data is not available to Javascript APIs then these APIs may behave as if no media data was present at all.</p>
    <p>Where media rendering is not performed by the UA, for example in the case of a hardware protected media pipeline, then the full set of HTML rendering capabilities, for example CSS Transforms, may not be available. One likely restriction is that
    video media may be constrained to appear only in rectangular regions with sides parallel to the edges of the window and with normal orientation.</p>

    <h2 id="events">3. Events</h2>

    <h3 id="event-definitions">3.1. Event Definitions</h3>
    <pre class="idl">
[Constructor(DOMString type, optional <precoderef>MediaKeyNeededEventInit</precoderef> eventInitDict)]
interface <precodedfn>MediaKeyNeededEvent</precodedfn> : <dom4ref name="event">Event</dom4ref> {
  readonly attribute DOMString <precoderef>type</precoderef>;
  readonly attribute Uint8Array? <precoderef>initData</precoderef>;
};

dictionary <precodedfn>MediaKeyNeededEventInit</precodedfn> : <dom4ref name="eventinit">EventInit</dom4ref> {
  DOMString <precoderef>type</precoderef>;
  Uint8Array? <precoderef>initData</precoderef>;
};</pre>

    <pre class="idl">
[Constructor(DOMString type, optional <precoderef>MediaKeyMessageEventInit</precoderef> eventInitDict)]
interface <precodedfn>MediaKeyMessageEvent</precodedfn> : <dom4ref name="event">Event</dom4ref> {
  readonly attribute Uint8Array <precoderef>message</precoderef>;
  readonly attribute DOMString? <precoderef>destinationURL</precoderef>;
};

dictionary <precodedfn>MediaKeyMessageEventInit</precodedfn> : <dom4ref name="eventinit">EventInit</dom4ref> {
  Uint8Array <precoderef>message</precoderef>;
  DOMString? <precoderef>destinationURL</precoderef>;
};</pre>

    <dl class="domintro">
     <dt><var title="">event</var> . <coderef>type</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the MIME type of the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> related to the event.</p>
     </dd>
     <dt><var title="">event</var> . <coderef>initData</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> related to the event.</p>
     </dd>
     <dt><var title="">event</var> . <coderef>message</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the message <span class="non-normative">(i.e. key request)</span> to send.</p>
     </dd>
     <dt><var title="">event</var> . <coderef>destinationURL</coderef></dt>
     <dd>
       <p>Returns the URL to send the <coderef>message</coderef> to.</p>
     </dd>
    </dl>
    <div class="impl">
    <p>The <codedfn>type</codedfn> attribute contains the MIME type of the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> specific to the event. The format of the <coderef>initData</coderef> will depend on the <coderef>type</coderef>.</p>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: MIME types usually include "audio/" or "video/", and user agents should include these in <var title="true">type</var> as appropriate.
    However, either variant may be returned for any stream of a given MIME type, and this is does not reflect the type(s) of stream(s) in the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>.
    Applications processing this attribute should handle all such variants.
    </p>
    <p>The <codedfn>initData</codedfn> attribute contains <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> specific to the event.</p>
    <p>The <codedfn>message</codedfn> attribute contains a message from the CDM. Messages are Key System-specific. <span class="non-normative">In most cases, it should be sent to a key server.</span></p>
    <p>The <codedfn>destinationURL</codedfn> is the URL to send the <coderef>message</coderef> to.
       An application <em>may</em> override this.
       <span class="non-normative">In some cases, it may have been provided by the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>.</span>
       It may be null.
    </p>
    </div>

    <h3 id="event-summary">3.2. Event Summary</h3>

    <p>The following event is fired at <coderef>HTMLMediaElement</coderef>.</p>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Event name</th>
          <th>Interface</th>
          <th>Dispatched when...</th>
          <th>Preconditions</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn>needkey</codedfn></td>
          <td><coderef>MediaKeyNeededEvent</coderef></td>
          <td>
            The user agent needs a key or license to begin or continue playback.
            <br></br><span class="non-normative"><br></br>It may have encountered <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> that may/does require decryption to load or play OR need a new key/license to continue playback.</span>
          </td>
          <td><readystate/> is equal to <have-metadata/> or greater.
          <span class="non-normative">It is possible that the element is playing or has played.</span>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>

    <p>The following events are fired at <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef>.</p>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Event name</th>
          <th>Interface</th>
          <th>Dispatched when...</th>
          <th>Preconditions</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="event">error</codedfn></td>
          <td><code><dom4ref name="event">Event</dom4ref></code></td>
          <td>An error occurs in the session. The session moves to the <coderef prefix="state">ERROR</coderef> state.</td>
          <td><!-- No Preconditions. --></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="event">message</codedfn></td>
          <td><coderef>MediaKeyMessageEvent</coderef></td>
          <td>
            A message has been generated <span class="non-normative">(and likely needs to be sent to a server)</span>.
            <span class="non-normative">For example, a key request has been generated as the result of a <methodref>createSession</methodref> call or another message must be sent in response to an <methodref>update</methodref> call.</span>
            The session moves to the <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef> state.
          </td>
          <td><!-- No Preconditions. --></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><codedfn prefix="event">ready</codedfn></td>
          <td><code><dom4ref name="event">Event</dom4ref></code></td>
          <td>
            The media element should not be blocked if encrypted data is encountered associated with the initData used to create the session. The session moves to the <coderef prefix="state">READY</coderef> state.
          </td>
          <td><!-- No Preconditions. --></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>


    <h2 id="algorithms">4. Algorithms</h2>

    <h3 id="algorithms-encrypted-stream">4.1. First Time a Key Reference is Encountered</h3>
    <p>The following steps are run when the <a href="#media-element">media element</a> encounters a source that may contain encrypted blocks or streams during the <resource-fetch-algorithm/>:</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>Let <var title="">initData</var> be null.</p></li>
      <li><p>If <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> was encountered, let <var title="">initData</var> be that initialization data.</p></li>
      <li><p>Follow the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
        <dl class="switch">
          <dt>If the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> is <cors-same-origin/></dt>
          <dd><Queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef>needkey</coderef> at the <a href="#media-element">media element</a>.
            <p>The event is of type <coderef>MediaKeyNeededEvent</coderef> and has:</p>
            <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
              <coderef>type</coderef> = the MIME type of the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> container format<br></br>
              <coderef>initData</coderef> = <var title="">initData</var>
            </li></ul>
            <p class="non-normative">Firing this event allows the application to begin acquiring the key process before it is needed.</p>
            <p class="non-normative">Note that <readystate/> is <em>not</em> changed and no algorithms are aborted. This event is merely informative.</p>
          </dd>
          <dt>Otherwise</dt>
          <dd>Abort the media element's <resource-fetch-algorithm/>, run the steps to report a <coderef>MEDIA_ERR_ENCRYPTED</coderef> error, and abort these steps.</dd>
        </dl>
      </li>

      <li><p><i>Continue Normal Flow</i>: Continue with the existing media element's <resource-fetch-algorithm/>.</p></li>
    </ol>

    <h3 id="algorithms-enrypted-block">4.2. Encrypted Block Encountered</h3>
    <p>The following steps are run when the <a href="#media-element">media element</a> encounters a block <span class="non-normative">(i.e. frame)</span> of encrypted <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> during the <resource-fetch-algorithm/>:</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>Follow the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
        <dl class="switch">
        <dt>If the media element's <coderef>keys</coderef> attribute is not null:</dt>
        <dd>Run the following steps:
          <ol>
            <li><p>Let <var title="true">cdm</var> be the <var title="true">cdm</var> loaded in the <a href="#dom-media-keys-constructor"><code>MediaKeys</code> constructor</a>.</p></li>
            <li><p>If <var title="true">cdm</var> has at least one <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> in the <coderef prefix="state">PENDING</coderef> or <coderef prefix="state">READY</coderef> state, run the following steps:</p>
              <p class="non-normative">This check ensures the <var title="true">cdm</var> has finished loading and is a prequisite for a matching key being available.</p>
            </li>
            <ol>
              <li><p>Let <var title="true">block key ID</var> be be the key ID for the current block.</p></li>
              <li><p>Use <var title="true">cdm</var> to decrypt the block by following the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
                <dl class="switch">
                <dt>If any session has a usable key for <var title="">block key ID</var></dt>
                <dd>Run the following steps:
                  <ol>
                    <li><p>Let <var title="">block key</var> be the matching key.</p>
                      <p class="non-normative">Note: If multiple sessions contain a <em>usable</em> key for <var title="">block key ID</var>, which session is used is <a href="#key-system">Key System</a>-dependent.</p>
                    </li>
                    <li><p>Use <var title="true">cdm</var> to decrypt the block using <var title="">block key</var> by following the steps for the first matching condition from the following list:</p>
                      <dl class="switch">
                        <dt>If decryption fails</dt>
                        <dd>Abort the media element's <resource-fetch-algorithm/>, run the steps to report a <videoref name="dom-mediaerror-media_err_decode">MEDIA_ERR_DECODE</videoref> error, and abort these steps.</dd>
                        <dt>Otherwise</dt>
                        <dd>Abort these steps and process the decrypted block as normal. <span class="non-normative">(Decode the block.)</span></dd>
                      </dl>
                      <p class="non-normative">Note: Not all decryption problems (i.e. using the wrong key) will result in a decryption failure. In such cases, no error is fired here but one may be fired during decode.</p>
                    </li>
                  </ol>
                </dd>
                <dt>If any session has an unusable key for <var title="">block key ID</var></dt>
                <dd>Run the following steps:
                  <ol>
                    <li><p>Let <var title="">session</var> be the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object for the session with an unusable key.</p></li>
                    <li><p>Create a new <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> object with the following attributes:</p>
                      <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
                        <coderef>code</coderef> = the appropriate <coderef>MediaKeyError</coderef> code<br></br>
                        <coderef>systemCode</coderef> = a Key System-specific value, if provided, and 0 otherwise
                      </li></ul>
                    </li>
                    <li><p>Set <var title="">session</var>'s <coderef>error</coderef> attribute to the error object created in the previous step.</p></li>
                    <li><p>Let the state of <var title="">session</var> be <coderef prefix="state">ERROR</coderef>.</p></li>
                    <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">error</coderef> at <var title="">session</var>.</p></li>
                  </ol>
                </dd>
                <dt><span class="non-normative">Otherwise (there is no key for <var title="true">block key ID</var> in any session)</span></dt>
                <dd><span class="non-normative">Continue.</span></dd>
                </dl>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </ol>
        </dd>
        <dt>If there is not an event handler for <coderef>needkey</coderef></dt>
        <dd>Abort the media element's <resource-fetch-algorithm/>, run the steps to report a <coderef>MEDIA_ERR_ENCRYPTED</coderef> error, and abort these steps.</dd>
      </dl>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Abort these steps and wait for a signal to resume playback.</p>
        <p class="non-normative">There is no usable key for the block.</p>
        <p class="non-normative">If playback stops because the stream cannot be decrypted when the <a href="#media-element">media element</a> is <videoref name="potentially-playing">potentially playing</videoref>, the media element is said to be <a href="#waiting-for-a-key">waiting for a key</a>.</p>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <div class="non-normative">
    <p>For frame-based encryption, this may be implemented as follows when the media element attempts to decode a frame as part of the <resource-fetch-algorithm/>:</p>
    <ol>
      <li><p>Let <var title="">encrypted</var> be false.</p></li>
      <li><p>Detect whether the frame is encrypted.</p>
        <dl class="switch">
          <dt>If the frame is encrypted</dt>
          <dd>Run the steps above.</dd>
          <dt>Otherwise</dt>
          <dd>Continue.</dd>
        </dl>
      </li>
      <li><p>Decode the frame.</p></li>
      <li><p>Provide the frame for rendering.</p></li>
    </ol>
    </div>

    <p>The following paragraph is added to <videoanchor name="playing-the-media-resource">Playing the media resource</videoanchor>.</p>
    <ul style="list-style-type:none">
    <li>A <a href="#media-element">media element</a> is said to be <dfn id="waiting-for-a-key">waiting for a key</dfn> when
    it would be <videoref name="potentially-playing">potentially playing</videoref> but
    the user agent has reached a point in the <videoref name="media-resource">media resource</videoref> that must be decrypted for the resource to continue and the <a href="#cdm">CDM</a> does not have the necessary key.
    </li>
    <li class="non-normative">The media element leaves this state when seeking but could re-enter it if the same conditions exist.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>At any point while decrypting content, the user agent may determine that a <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> is no longer needed. It must run the following steps:</p>
    <ol>
        <li><p>Let the state of the session be <coderef prefix="state">CLOSED</coderef>.</p></li>
        <li><p><queue-a-task/> to <fire-a-simple-event/> named <coderef prefix="event">closed</coderef> at the <coderef>MediaKeySession</coderef> object.</p></li>
    </ol>
  
    <h3 id="algorithms-load">4.3. Addition to Media Element Load Algorithm</h3>
    <p>The following step is added to the existing <media-element-load-algorithm/>:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><p>Clear the <coderef>keys</coderef> attribute for this <a href="#media-element">media element</a>.</p>
      <p class="non-normative">This also means the <coderef>keys</coderef> attribute will be cleared when the <videoref name="attr-media-src">src</videoref> attribute is set or changed per <videoanchor name="location-of-the-media-resource">Location of the media resource</videoanchor></p>
      </li>
    </ul>


    <h2 id="key-release">5. Key Release</h2>
    <p class="non-normative">Note: it is an open issue whether further normative specification of this feature is required. See <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=17199">Bug 17199</a>.</p>
    <h3 id="key-release-intro">5.1. Introduction</h3>
    <non-normative-section/>
    <p>The above sections provide for delivery of key/license information to a <a href="#cdm">Content Decryption Module</a>.
    This section provides for management of the entire key/license lifecycle, that is, secure proof of key release.
    Use cases for such proof include any service where is it necessary for the service to know, reliably, which granted keys/licenses are still available for use by the user and which have been deleted.
    Examples include a service with restrictions on the number of concurrent streams available to a user or a service where content is available on a rental basis, for use offline.
    </p>
    
    <p>Secure proof of key release must necessarily involve the CDM due to the relative ease with which scripts may be modified.
    The CDM must provide a message asserting, in a CDM-specific form, that a specific key or license has been destroyed.
    Such messages must be cached in the CDM until acknowledgement of their delivery to the service has been received.
    This acknowledgement must also be in the form of a CDM-specific message.
    </p>
    
    <p>The mechanism for secure proof of key release operates outside the scope of any <a href="#media-element">media element</a>.
    This is because proof-of-release messages may be cached in CDMs after the associated media elements have been destroyed.
    Proof-of-key-release messages are subject to the same origin policy: they shall only be delivered to scripts with the same origin as the script which created the media element that provided the key/license.
    </p>


    <h2 id="simple-decryption">6. Simple Decryption</h2>
    <p>All user agents must support the simple decryption capabilities described in this section regardless of whether they support a more advanced <a href="#cdm">CDM</a>.
    <span class="non-normative">This ensures that there is a common baseline level of protection that is guaranteed to be supported in all user agents, including those that are entirely open source.
    Thus, content providers that need only basic protection can build simple applications that will work on all platforms without needing to work with any content protection providers.</span>
    </p>

    <h3 id="simple-decryption-clear-key">6.1. Clear Key</h3>
    <p>The "org.w3.clearkey" <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> indicates a plain-text clear (unencrypted) key will be used to decrypt the source.
    No additional client-side content protection is required.
    Use of this Key System is described below.
    </p>
    
    <p>The <var title="true">keySystem</var> parameter and <coderef>keySystem</coderef> attributes are always <code>"org.w3.clearkey"</code>.
    The <coderef>sessionId</coderef> string is numerical.</p>

    <p>The <coderef>initData</coderef> attribute of the <coderef>needkey</coderef> event and the <var title="true">initData</var> parameter of <methodref>createSession</methodref> are the same container-specific <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> format and values.
    <span class="non-normative">
    If supported, these values should provide some type of identification of the content or key that could be used to look up the key (since there is no defined logic for parsing it).
    For containers that support a simple key ID, it should be a binary array containing the raw key ID.
    For other containers, it may be some other opaque blob or null.</span>
    </p>

    
    <p>The <coderef>MediaKeyMessageEvent</coderef> generated by <methodref>createSession</methodref> has:</p>
    <ul style="list-style-type:none"><li>
      <coderef>message</coderef> = a container-specific value extracted from the <var title="true">initData</var> parameter of <methodref>createSession</methodref>. null if <var title="true">initData</var> was null or a value could not be extracted.<br></br>
      <coderef>destinationURL</coderef> = value of the default URL if present in the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor> and null otherwise.
    </li></ul>

    <p>The <var title="true">response</var> parameter of <methodref>update</methodref> should be a JSON Web Key (JWK) representation of the symmetric key to be used for decryption, as defined in the <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-jose-json-web-key">IETF Internet-draft JSON Web Key (JWK) specification</a>. The JSON string is encoded into the Uint8Array parameter using <ascii-encoding />.</p>
    <p>When the JWK 'key type' ("kty") member value is 'octet sequence' ("oct"), the 'key value' ("k") member will be a base64 encoding of the octet sequence containing the symmetric key value.</p>
    <p>For example, the following contains a single symmetric key represented as a JWK, designated as being for use with the AES Key Wrap algorithm (line breaks for readability, only).</p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
{
  "keys": 
    [{
      "kty":"oct",
      "alg":"A128KW",
      "kid":"67ef0gd8pvfd0=",
      "k":"GawgguFyGrWKav7AX4VKUg"
    }]
}</pre>
    </div>

    <h2 id="security">7. Security Considerations</h2>
    <non-normative-section/>
    
    <p>Key system implementations must consider initialization data, key data and media data as potential attack vectors and must take care to safely parse, decrypt etc. initialization data, key data and media data. User Agents may want to validate data before passing it to the CDM, especially if the CDM does not run in the same (sandboxed) context as the DOM (i.e. rendering). </p>
    <p>It is STRONGLY RECOMMENDED that key data and media data do not contain active content [<a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4949.txt>" title="Shirey, R., Internet Security Glossary, Version 2, RFC 4949, August 2007, IETF">SECURITY GLOSSARY</a>].  If a Key System implementation supports the interpretation or execution of such active content then it is STRONGLY RECOMMENDED that User Agents make use of sandbox techniques to restrict the scope of access that the CDM has to the user's device. In any case, User Agent and Key System implementers should consider the threats, risks, and safeguards described in [<span title="Jansen, W, et al., Guidelines on Active Content and Mobile Code, Special Publication 800-28, Version 2, 2008, National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)">ACTIVE CONTENT</span>].</p>
    <p>User Agents are responsible for providing users with a secure way to browse the web. Since User Agents may integrate with third party CDM implementations, CDM implementors must provide sufficient information and controls to user agent implementors to enable them to properly asses the security implications of integrating with the Key System.</p>
    <p>Note: unsandboxed CDMs (or CDMs that use platform features) and UAs that use them must be especially careful in all areas of security, including parsing of key and media data, etc. due to the potential for compromises to provide access to OS/platform features, interact with or run as root, access drivers, kernel, firmware, hardware, etc., all of which may not be written to be robust against hostile software or web-based attacks. Additionally, CDMs may not be updated with security fixes as frequently, especially when part of the OS, platform or hardware.</p>
    
    <h2 id="privacy">8. Privacy Considerations</h2>
    <non-normative-section/>

    <p>The presence or use of Key Systems on a user's device raises a number of privacy issues, falling into two categories: (a) user-specific information that may be disclosed by the EME interface itself, or within messages from Key Systems and (b) user-specific information that may be persistently stored on the users device.</p>
    <p>User Agents should take responsibility for providing users with adequate control over their own privacy. Since User Agents may integrate with third party CDM implementations, CDM implementors must provide sufficient information and controls to user agent implementors to enable them to implement appropriate techniques to ensure users have control over their privacy, including but not limited to the techniques described below.</p>

    <h3>8.1. Information disclosed by EME and Key Systems</h3>
    <p>Concerns regarding information disclosed by EME and Key Systems fall into two categories, concerns about non-specific information that may nevertheless contribute to the possibility of fingerprinting a user agent or device and user-specific information that may be used directly for user tracking.</p>

    <h4>8.1.1 Fingerprinting</h4>
    <p>Malicious applications may be able to fingerprint users or user agents by detecting or enumerating the list of key systems that are supported and related information. If proper origin protections are not provided this could include detection of sites that have been visited and information stored for those sites. In particular, Key Systems should not share key or other data between sites that are not CORS-same-origin.</p>

    <h4>8.1.2 Tracking</h4>
    <p>User-specific information may be obtained over the EME API in two ways: through detection of stored keys and through Key System messages.</p>

    <p>Key Systems may access or create persistent or semi-persistent identifiers for a device or user of a device. In some cases these identifiers may be bound to a specific device in a secure manner. If these identifiers are present in Key System messages, then devices and/or users may be tracked. If the mitigations below are applied this could include both tracking of users / devices over time and associating multiple users of a given device. If not mitigated, such tracking may take three forms depending on the design of the Key System:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>in all cases, such identifiers are expected to be available to sites and/or servers that fully support the Key System (and thus can interpret Key System messages) enabling tracking by such sites.</li>
      <li>if identifiers exposed by Key Systems are not origin-specific, then two sites and/or servers that fully support the Key System may collude to track the user</li>
      <li>if a Key System messages contains information derived from a user identifier in a consistent manner, for example such that a portion of the initial Key System message for a specific content item does not change over time and is dependent on the user identifier, then this information could be used by any application to track the device or user over time.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>If a Key System permits keys to be stored and to be re-used between origins, then it may be possible for two origins to collude and track a unique user by recording their ability to access a common key.</p>
    <p>Finally, if any user interface for user control of Key Systems presents data separately from data in HTTP session cookies or persistent storage, then users are likely to modify site authorization or delete data in one and not the others. This would allow sites to use the various features as redundant backup for each other, defeating a user's attempts to protect his privacy.</p>
    <p>There are a number of techniques that can be used to mitigate these risks of tracking without user consent:</p>

    <dl>
      <dt>User deletion of persistent identifiers</dt>
      <dd>User agents could provide users with the ability to clear any persistent identifiers maintained by Key Systems.</dd>

      <dt>Use of (non-reversible) per-origin identifiers</dt>
      <dd>The user / device identifier exposed by a Key System may be different for each origin, either by allocation of different identifiers for different origins or by use of a non-reversible origin-specific mapping from an origin-independent identifier.</dd>

      <dt>Encryption of user identifiers</dt>
      <dd>User identifiers in Key System messages could be encrypted, together with a timestamp or nonce, such that the Key System messages are always different. This would prevent the use of Key System messages for tracking except by applications fully supporting the Key System.</dd>

      <dt>Site-specific white-listing of access to each Key System</dt>
      <dd>User agents could require the user to explicitly authorize access by each site to each Key System. User agents should enable users to revoke this authorization either temporarily or permanently.</dd>

      <dt>Treating Key System persistent identifiers as cookies</dt>
      <dd>User agents should present the presence of persistent identifiers stored by Key Systems to the user in a way that associates them strongly with HTTP session cookies. This might encourage users to view such identifiers with healthy suspicion.</dd>

      <dt>Shared blacklists</dt>
      <dd>User agents may allow users to share their Key System domain blacklists. This would allow communities to act together to protect their privacy.</dd>

      <dt>User alerts / prompts</dt>
      <dd>User Agents could ensure that users are fully informed and / or give explicit consent before identifiers are exposed in messages from Key Systems.</dd>

      <dt>User controls to disable Key Systems or Key System use of identifiers</dt>
      <dd>User Agents could provide users with a global control of whether a Key System is enabled / disabled and / or whether Key System use of user / device identifiers is enabled or disabled (if supported by the Key System).</dd>
    </dl>

    <p>While these suggestions prevent trivial use of this feature for user tracking, they do not block it altogether. Within a single domain, a site can continue to track the user during a session, and can then pass all this information to a third party along with any identifying information (names, credit card numbers, addresses) obtained by the site. If a third party cooperates with multiple sites to obtain such information, and if identifiers are not per-origin, then a profile can still be created.</p>
    <p>It is important to note that identifiers that are non-clearable, non-origin-specific or hardware-bound exceed the tracking impact of existing techniques such as Cookies or session identifiers embedded in URLs.</p>
    <p>Thus, in addition to the various mitigations described above, if a browser supports a mode of operation intended to preserve user anonymity, then User Agent implementers should carefully consider whether access to Key Systems should be disabled in this mode.</p>
      
    <h3>8.2. Information stored on user devices</h3>
    <p>Key Systems may store information on a user's device, or user agents may store information on behalf of Key Systems. Potentially, this could reveal information about a user to another user of the same device, including potentially the origins that have used a particular Key System (i.e. sites visited) or even the content that has been decrypted using a Key System.</p>
    <p>If information stored by one origin affects the operation of the Key System for another origin, then potentially the sites visited or content viewed by a user on one site may be revealed to another, potentially malicious, site.</p>
    <p>There are a number of techniques that can be used to mitigate these privacy risk to users:</p>

    <dl>
      <dt>Origin-specific Key System storage</dt>
      <dd>User agents may require that some or all of the Key System's persistently stored data is stored in an origin-specific way.</dd>

      <dt>User deletion of Key System storage</dt>
      <dd>User agents may present the user with a way to delete Key System storage for a specific origin or all origins.</dd>

      <dt>Treating Key System stored data like cookies / Web Storage</dt>
      <dd>User agents should present the presence of persistent data stored by Key Systems to the user in a way that associates it strongly with HTTP session cookies and/or Web Storage. This might encourage users to view such data with healthy suspicion.</dd>

      <dt>Encryption or obfuscation of Key System stored data</dt>
      <dd>User agents should treat data stored by Key Systems as potentially sensitive; it is quite possible for user privacy to be compromised by the release of this information. To this end, user agents should ensure that such data is securely stored and when deleting data, it is promptly deleted from the underlying storage.</dd>
    </dl>

    <h2 id="containers">9. Container Guidelines</h2>
    <p>This document describes behavior independent of specific media containers.
    The following sections provide container-specific details for implementations that choose to support those containers.
    </p>
    
    <h3 id="webm">9.1 WebM</h3>
    <div class="nonnormative">
      <p>This section defines the stream format and Initialization Data for implementations that choose to support <a href="http://www.webmproject.org/code/specs/container/">WebM</a>.</p>

      <h4 id="webm-stream-format">9.1.1.Stream Format </h4>
      <p><a href="http://wiki.webmproject.org/encryption/webm-encryption-rfc">Encrypted WebM streams</a> are encrypted at the block level with AES-128 CTR encryption.
      The container shall include appropriate values within the <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncryption">ContentEncryption</a> element.
      </p>

      <p>WebM streams may be partially encrypted, both at the <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#LevelTrack">Track</a> level and the block level.
      In the former case, a subset of Tracks in the stream have a <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncryption">ContentEncryption</a> element.
      In the latter case, a subset of the blocks within a Track containing a <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncryption">ContentEncryption</a> element are marked as encrypted.</p>

      <h4 id="webm-detect-encrypt">9.1.2. Detecting Encryption</h4>
      <p>When a WebM <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#LevelTrack">Track</a> is parsed, the presence of a <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncKeyID">ContentEncKeyID</a> element shall indicate that the stream is potentially encrypted. Each time a new value is encountered in a ContentEncKeyID element, the <a href="#algorithms-encrypted-stream">First Time a Key Reference is Encountered</a> algorithm shall be invoked with the value in that element as <var title="">initData</var>.</p>

      <p><a href="#algorithms-enrypted-block">Encrypted blocks</a> are those marked encrypted by the <a href="http://wiki.webmproject.org/encryption/webm-encryption-rfc#TOC-4.6-Signal-Byte-Format">Signal Byte.</a></p>

      <h4 id="webm-init-data">9.1.3. Initialization Data and Events</h4>
      <p><a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> in <a href="#events">events</a> is always a key ID, which is the <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncKeyID">ContentEncKeyID</a> of the current <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#LevelTrack">Track</a>.
      The current Track is the one being parsed or that contains the block being decrypted.
      </p>

      <p>Events only contain a single key ID.
      However, if supported by the key system, multiple key IDs may be bundled by the application before requesting a key and multiple key ID-key pairs may be returned by the license server.
      </p>

      <p>An event will be fired for each new key ID (in <a href="http://matroska.org/technical/specs/index.html#ContentEncKeyID">ContentEncKeyID</a>) encountered for which a key is not already known.</p>
    </div>

    <h3 id="iso">9.2 ISO Base Media File Format</h3>
    <div class="nonnormative">
      <div class="issue"><div class="issue-title"><span>Issue 4</span></div>Note: There is an open issue about how initialization data should be extracted from ISO BMFF content. See <a href="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=17673">Bug 17673</a>.</div>
      <p>This section defines the stream format and initialization data for ISO Base media File Format (ISOBMFF) content.</p>

      <h4 id="iso-stream-format">9.2.1 Stream format</h4>
      <p>The stream format is dependent upon the protection scheme, as defined in the scheme type box ('schm').</p>
      <p>For example, under the common encryption ("cenc") protection scheme, ISOBMFF content is encrypted at the sample level with AES-128 CTR encryption, according to ISO/IEC 23001-7:2012, "Information technology - MPEG system technologies - Part 7: Common encryption in ISO base media file format files". This protection method enables multiple Key Systems to decrypt the same media content.</p>

      <h4 id="iso-detect-encrypt">9.2.2 Detecting Encryption</h4>
      <p>Protection scheme signaling conforms with ISO/IEC 14496-12. When protection has been applied, the stream type will be transformed to 'encv' for video or 'enca' for audio, with a scheme information box ('sinf') added to the sample entry in the sample description box ('stsd'). The scheme information box ('sinf') will contain a scheme type box ('schm') with a scheme_type field set to the 4CC value of the protection scheme.</p>
      <p>Additionally, if the protection scheme is common encryption ("cenc"), the "encrypted block" is a sample. Determining whether a sample is encrypted depends on the corresponding track encryption box ('tenc') and the sample group associated with the sample. In this case the default encryption state of a sample is defined by the IsEncrypted flag in the associated track encryption box ('tenc'). This default state may be modified by the IsEncrypted flag in the Sample Group Description Box ('sgpd'), pointed to by an index in the Sample to Group Box ('sbgp').</p>
      <p>For complete information about "cenc" see ISO/IEC 23001-7:2012.</p>

      <h4 id="iso-init-data">9.2.3 Initialization Data and Events</h4>
      <p>For ISOBMFF the InitData begins with a the protection scheme information box ('sinf'). The 'sinf' includes the scheme type box ('schm'), giving the scheme_type, and the scheme information box ('schi').</p>
      <p>If this scheme_type is common encryption ("cenc"), the scheme information box will also contain the track encryption box ('tenc'), giving the defaults for IsEncrypted, IV_size and KID for that track. In addition, one or more protection system specific heder boxes ('pssh') will be concatenated after the 'sinf' box.</p>
      <p>In a file encrypted with common encryption, each key is identified by a Key ID and each encrypted sample is associated with the Key ID of the key needed to decrypt it. This association is signaled either through the specification of a default Key ID in the track encryption box ('tenc') or by assigning the sample to a Sample Group, the definition of which specifies a Key ID. Common encryption files may contain a mixture of encrypted and unencrypted samples. Playback of unencrypted samples should not be impeded by unavailability of the keys needed to decrypt other samples in the same file or track.</p>
      <p>Note that if there is already an active Key System CDM and the key storage for that Key System already contains the key associated with the Key ID, there is no need to generate a needkey event.</p>
    </div>
    

    <h2 id="examples">10. Examples</h2>
    <non-normative-sections/>
    <p>This section contains example solutions for various use cases using the proposed extensions.
    These are not the only solutions to these use cases.
    Video elements are used in the examples, but the same would apply to all <a href="#media-element">media element</a>s.
    In some cases, such as using synchronous XHR, the examples are simplified to keep the focus on the extensions.
    </p>

    <h3 id="example-source-and-key-known" class="exampleheader">10.1. Source and Key Known at Page Load (Clear Key Encryption)</h3>
    <p class="exampledescription">In this simple example, the source file and <a href="#simple-decryption-clear-key">clear-text key</a> are hard-coded in the page.</p>
    <p class="exampledescription">This example is very simple because it does not care when the key has been added or associating that event with the <methodref>update</methodref> call. It also does not handle errors.</p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
&lt;script&gt;
  function load() {
    var video = document.getElementById("video");

    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      video.<premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(new <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>("org.w3.clearkey"));
    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      throw "Could not create MediaKeys";

    var keySession = video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>.<premethodref>createSession</premethodref>();
    if (!keySession)
      throw "Could not create key session";

    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">message</precoderef>", handleMessage, false);
  }

  function handleMessage(event) {
    var keySession = event.target;

    var key = new Uint8Array([ ... ]);
    keySession.<premethodref>update</premethodref>(key);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;body onload="load()"&gt;
  &lt;video src="foo.webm" autoplay id="video"&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;</pre>
    </div>

    <h3 id="example-source-known-but-key-not-known" class="exampleheader">10.2. Source Known but Key Not Known at Page Load</h3>
    <p class="exampledescription">In this case, the <a href="#initialization-data">Initialization Data</a> is contained in the <videoanchor name="media-data">media data</videoanchor>.
    If this was not the case, <code>handleKeyNeeded()</code> could obtain and provide it instead of getting it from the event.</p>

    <h4 id="example-clear-key" class="exampleheader">10.2.1. Clear Key Encryption</h4>
    <p class="exampledescription">This solution uses the <a href="#simple-decryption-clear-key">Clear Key</a> <a href="#simple-decryption">Simple Decryption</a>.</p>
    <p class="exampledescription">As with the previous example, this one is very simple because it does not care when the key has been added or handle errors.</p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
&lt;script&gt;
  function handleKeyNeeded(event) {
    var video = event.target;

    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      video.<premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(new <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>("org.w3.clearkey"));
    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      throw "Could not create MediaKeys";

    var keySession = video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>.<premethodref>createSession</premethodref>(event.<precoderef>type</precoderef>, event.<precoderef>initData</precoderef>);
    if (!keySession)
      throw "Could not create key session";

    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">message</precoderef>", handleMessage, false);
  }

  function handleMessage(event) {
    var keySession = event.target;
    var message = event.<precoderef>message</precoderef>;

    var xmlhttp = new XMLHttpRequest();
    xmlhttp.open("POST", "http://.../getkey");
    xmlhttp.onreadystatechange = function() {
      if(xmlhttp.readyState==4) {
        var key = new Uint8Array(xmlhttp.response);
        keySession.<premethodref>update</premethodref>(key);
      }
    }
    xmlhttp.send(message);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video src="foo.webm" autoplay on<precoderef>needkey</precoderef>="handleKeyNeeded(event)"&gt;&lt;/video&gt;</pre>
    </div>

    <h4 id="example-other-cdm" class="exampleheader">10.2.2. Other Content Decryption Module</h4>
    <p class="exampledescription">This solution uses more advanced decryption from a fictitious <a href="#cdm">content decryption module</a> called Some System.</p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
&lt;script&gt;
  function handleKeyNeeded(event) {
    var video = event.target;

    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      video.<premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(new <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>("com.example.somesystem.1_0"));
    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      throw "Could not create MediaKeys";

    var keySession = video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>.<premethodref>createSession</premethodref>(event.<precoderef>type</precoderef>, event.<precoderef>initData</precoderef>);
    if (!keySession)
      throw "Could not create key session";

    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">message</precoderef>", licenseRequestReady, false);
  }

  function licenseRequestReady(event) {
    var keySession = event.target;
    var request = event.<precoderef>message</precoderef>;
    if (!request)
      throw "Could not create license request";

    var xmlhttp = new XMLHttpRequest();
    xmlhttp.open("POST", "http://.../getkey");
    xmlhttp.onreadystatechange = function() {
      if(xmlhttp.readyState==4) {
        var license = new Uint8Array(xmlhttp.response);
        keySession.<premethodref>update</premethodref>(license);
      }
    }
    xmlhttp.send(request);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video src="foo.webm" autoplay on<precoderef>needkey</precoderef>="handleKeyNeeded(event)"&gt;&lt;/video&gt;</pre>
    </div>

    <h3 id="examples-selecting-key-system" class="exampleheader">10.3. Selecting a Supported Key System</h3>
    <p class="exampledescription">Below is an example of detecting supported <a href="#key-system">Key System</a> using the <methodref>isTypeSupported</methodref> and selecting one.
    </p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
&lt;script&gt;
  var keySystem;
  var licenseUrl;

  function selectKeySystem() {
    if (<precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>.<premethodref>isTypeSupported</premethodref>("com.example.somesystem", "video/webm; codecs='vp8, vorbis'")) {
      licenseUrl = "https://license.example.com/getkey"; // OR "https://example.&lt;My Video Site domain&gt;"
      keySystem = "com.example.somesystem";
    } else if (<precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>.<premethodref>isTypeSupported</premethodref>("com.foobar", "video/webm; codecs='vp8, vorbis'")) {
      licenseUrl = "https://license.foobar.com/request";
      keySystem = "com.foobar";
    } else {
      throw "Key System not supported";
    }
  }

  function handleKeyNeeded(event) {
    var video = event.target;

    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>) {
      selectKeySystem();
      video.<premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(new <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>(keySystem));
    }
    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      throw "Could not create MediaKeys";

    var keySession = video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>.<premethodref>createSession</premethodref>(event.<precoderef>type</precoderef>, event.<precoderef>initData</precoderef>);
    if (!keySession)
      throw "Could not create key session";

    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">message</precoderef>", licenseRequestReady, false);
  }
  
  function licenseRequestReady(event) {
    var keySession = event.target;
    var request = event.<precoderef>message</precoderef>;
    if (!request)
      throw "Could not create license request";

    var xmlhttp = new XMLHttpRequest();
    xmlhttp.open("POST", licenseUrl);
    xmlhttp.onreadystatechange = function() {
      if(xmlhttp.readyState==4) {
        var license = new Uint8Array(xmlhttp.response);
        keySession.<premethodref>update</premethodref>(license);
      }
    }
    xmlhttp.send(request);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video src="foo.webm" autoplay on<precoderef>needkey</precoderef>="handleKeyNeeded(event)"&gt;&lt;/video&gt;</pre>
    </div>

    <h3 id="example-using-all-events" class="exampleheader">10.4. Using All Events</h3>
    <p class="exampledescription">This is a more complete example showing all events being used.</p>
    <p class="exampledescription">Note that <code>handleMessage</code> could be called multiple times, including in response to the <methodref>update</methodref> call if multiple round trips are required and for any other reason the Key System might need to send a message.</p>

    <div class="example">
      <pre class="code">
&lt;script&gt;
  var keySystem;
  var licenseUrl;

  function handleMessageResponse() {
    var license = new Uint8Array(xmlhttp.response);
    this.keySession.<premethodref>update</premethodref>(license);
  }
  
  function sendMessage(message, keySession) {
    xmlhttp = new XMLHttpRequest();
    xmlhttp.keySession = keySession;
    xmlhttp.onreadystatechange = handleMessageResponse;
    xmlhttp.open("POST", licenseUrl);
    xmlhttp.send(message);
  }

  function handleMessage(event) {
    var keySession = event.target;
    var message = event.<precoderef>message</precoderef>;
    if (!message)
      throw "Invalid key message";
  
    sendMessage(message, keySession);
  }

  function handleReady(event) {
    // Do some bookkeeping with event.target.<precoderef>sessionId</precoderef> if necessary.
  }

  function handleError(event) {
    // Report event.target.error.<precoderef>code</precoderef> and event.target.error.<precoderef>systemCode</precoderef>,
    // and do some bookkeeping with event.target.<precoderef>sessionId</precoderef> if necessary.
  }

  function handleKeyNeeded(event) {
    var video = event.target;

    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>) {
      selectKeySystem();  // See previous example for implementation.
      video.<premethodref>setMediaKeys</premethodref>(new <precoderef>MediaKeys</precoderef>(keySystem));
    }
    if (!video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>)
      throw "Could not create MediaKeys";

    var keySession = video.<precoderef>keys</precoderef>.<premethodref>createSession</premethodref>(event.<precoderef>type</precoderef>, event.<precoderef>initData</precoderef>);
    if (!keySession)
      throw "Could not create key session";

    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">message</precoderef>", handleMessage, false);
    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">ready</precoderef>", handleReady, false);
    keySession.addEventListener("<precoderef prefix="event">error</precoderef>", handleError, false);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video src="foo.webm" autoplay on<precoderef>needkey</precoderef>="handleKeyNeeded(event)"&gt;&lt;/video&gt;</pre>
    </div>


    <h2 id="revision-history">11. Revision History</h2>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Version</th>
          <th>Comment</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>17 September 2013</td>
          <td>Produced candidate WD.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>6 May 2013</td>
          <td>Produced updated candidate FPWD.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>14 January 2013</td>
          <td>Produced candidate FPWD.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>16 August 2012</td>
          <td>Converted to the object-oriented API.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/eme-v0.1b/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html">0.1b</a></td>
          <td>Last non-object-oriented revision.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/eme-v0.1a/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html">0.1a</a></td>
          <td>Corrects minor mistakes in 0.1.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="http://dvcs.w3.org/hg/html-media/raw-file/eme-v0.1/encrypted-media/encrypted-media.html">0.1</a></td>
          <td>Initial Proposal</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </body>
</html>
